<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  
  <artheader>
    <title>Unified Performance tool for networking (uperf)</title>
    <!--
    <author>
      <firstname>Neelakanth</firstname><surname>Nadgir</surname>
      <email>neel@sun.com</email>
    </author>
    and
    <author>
      <firstname>SIP Team, PAE Sun Microsystems</firstname>      
    </author>
    -->
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Unified Performance Tool or uperf for short, is a network
        performance measurement tool that supports execution of
        workload profiles
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </artheader>
  
  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Microbenchmarks rarely measure real world performance. This
      is especially true in networking where applications can use
      multiple protocols, use different types of communication,
      interleave CPU processing with communication, etc. However,
      popular microbenchmarks like iPerf and netperf are very
      simplistic, supporting only one protocol at a time, fixed
      message sized communication, no support for interleaving CPU
      processing between communication, and so on. Thus there is a need for
      a tool to closely model real world performance.
    </para>
    <para>
      Uperf (Unifed performance tool for networking) solves this
      problem by allowing the user to model the real world
      application using a very high level language (called
      profile) and running this over the network. It allows the
      user to use multiple protocols, varying message sizes for
      communication, a 1xN communication model, support for
      collection of CPU counter statistics, and much more. 
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Features</title>
      <para> 
        The following list is a short overview of some of the features supported
        by uperf:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>Support modeling of workloads using profiles</listitem>
          <listitem>Support for Multiple protocols (new protocols can 
            be easily integrated). The following protocols
            are currently supported.
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>TCP</listitem>
              <listitem>UDP</listitem>
              <listitem>SCTP</listitem>
              <listitem>SSL</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
	  <listitem>Support for IPV4 and IPV6</listitem>
          <listitem>1-Many hosts</listitem>
          <listitem>Support for CPU counters and lots of other detailed
          statistics</listitem>
          <listitem>Ability to choose whether to use processes or threads</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Supported Platforms</title>
      <para>Uperf is supported on Linux, FreeBSD, MacOS, Solaris and
	      OpenSolaris. 
      </para> 
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <para>
	      uperf was originally developed by the Performance Availablity
	      Engineering 
        group at Sun Microsystems. It was originally developed by
        <ulink url="http://blogs.sun.com/realneel">Neelakanth Nadgir</ulink>
        and <ulink url="mailto:nitin.rammanavar@sun.com">Nitin Rammanavar</ulink>.
        <ulink url="mailto:J.Zhang@sun.com">Jing Zhang</ulink> added support 
        for the uperf harness. <ulink url="mailto:Chaoyue.Xiong">Joy</ulink>
        added SSL support, and <ulink url="mailto:ding.he@sun.com">Eric He</ulink>
        ported it to windows and is currently a core contributer. 
        <ulink url="mailto:charles.suresh@sun.com">Charles Suresh</ulink>,
        <ulink url="mailto:alan.chiu@sun.com">Alan Chiu</ulink>, 
        <ulink url="mailto:janlung.sung@sun.com">Jan-Lung Sung</ulink> have 
        contributed significantly to its design and development.
      </para>
      <para>
	      After it was opensourced, Michael Tuexen has contributed
	      significanlty to the project, espcially in the areas of IPV6
	      and SCTP support. Michael and Irene Ruengeler added support
	      for several SCTP options.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1><title>Using uperf</title>
    <sect2><title>Getting uperf</title>
      <para>
        uperf is opensource software using the 
        <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-2.0.txt">
          GNU General Public License v2
        </ulink>.
        You can download it from <ulink url="http://uperf.org" />. Binaries are 
        available for Solaris and Linux.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Running uperf</title>
      <para>
        uperf can be run as either a master(active) or a slave(passive).
        When run as active it needs master flag(-m) with a profile
        describing the test application. 
        <programlisting><xi:include  href="uperf-help.txt"  parse="text"  
                                       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
	uperf comes bundled with quite a few sample profiles in the
	<filename class="directory">workloads</filename> directory. You
	can always tweak them to suit your needs or write your own
	profile. Several of these profiles pick up values (like
	<parameter>remotehost</parameter>, or
	<parameter>protocol</parameter>) from the ENVIRONMENT. These
	variables begin with the $ sign in the profile. You can either
	set these (via <code>export h=192.168.1.4</code>) or hardcode
	them in the profile.
      </para>
      <para>
        The list of profiles included by uperf is as follows
        
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>netperf.xml</term>
            <listitem><para>
		This profile represents the request-response kind of
		traffic.  One thread on the master is reading and
		writing 90 bytes of data from the slave. The remote end
		(slave) address is specified via the
		<parameter>$h</parameter> environment variable.
		<parameter>$proto</parameter> specifies the protocol to
		be used.
		</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          
          <varlistentry>
            <term>iperf.xml</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
		In this profile, multiple threads simulates one way
		traffic (8K size) between two hosts (similar to the
		iperf networking tool) for 30 seconds.
                <parameter>$h</parameter> specifies the remote host, 
                <parameter>$proto</parameter> specifies the protocol, and
                <parameter>$nthr</parameter> specifies the numnber of threads.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>connect.xml</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
		In this profile, multiple threads try to connect and
		disconnect from the remote host. This can be used to
		measure the connection setup performance.
		<parameter>$nthr</parameter> specifies the numnber of
		threads, and <parameter>$iter</parameter> determines
		number of connects and disconnects each thread will do.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry> 
          <varlistentry>
            <term>two-hosts.xml</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
		This profile demonstrates an application in which each
		thread opens a connection each to two hosts, and then
		reads 200 bytes from the first connection and writes it
		to the other connection.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <!--
          <varlistentry>
            <term>SAM.xml</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          -->
          
          
        </variablelist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1><title>Uperf profiles</title>
    <para>
      uperf is based on the idea that you can describe your
      application or workload in very general terms and the
      framework will run that application or workload for you. For
      example, if you are familiar with netperf or
      request-response microbenchmarks, this general description
      would be 
      <emphasis>"each thread sends 100bytes and receives 100 bytes using
      UDP"</emphasis>. For a more complex application, we may have to
      specify the number of connections, and/or the number of threads,
      are the threads all doing the same kind of operation, what
      protocols are being used, Is the traffic bursty?, etc. As you can
      see, it gets quite complicated for any real-world application.
      uperf defines a language to specify all of these information in a
      machine-understandable format (xml) called a
      <emphasis>profile</emphasis>. uperf then parses and runs whatever
      the profile specifies. The user has to specify the profile for the
      master only. uperf automatically transforms the profile for the
      slaves and uses it.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The profile needs to be a valid XML file. Variables that begin with a 
      '<emphasis>$</emphasis>' are picked up from the ENVIRONMENT.
    </para>
    <sect2><title>Sample Profile</title>
      <para>
        A sample profile for the request-response microbenchmark
        is shown below.
        <programlisting><xi:include  href="netperf.xml.txt"  parse="text"  
                           xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
        </programlisting>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Explanation of profile</title>
      <para>
        Every profile begins with a xml header that specifies that
        it is a XML file. A profile has <emphasis>name</emphasis>.
        This is used to identify the name of the profile, and is not
        used by uperf. 
        The major parts of a profile are
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>group</listitem>
          <listitem>transaction</listitem>
          <listitem>flowop</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      Lets look at each of these in detail.
      
      <sect3><title>Group</title>
        A profile can have multiple
        <emphasis>group</emphasis>s. A <emphasis>group</emphasis> is
        a collection of threads or processes that execute
        <emphasis>transaction</emphasis>s contained in that group.
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>Transaction</title>
        A <emphasis>transaction</emphasis> is a unit of work.
        Transactions have either an <emphasis>iteration</emphasis>
        or a <emphasis>duration</emphasis> associated with it. If
        <code>&lt;transaction iteration=1000&gt;</code> is specified,
        the contents of the transactions are executed 1000 times. If
        <code>&lt;transaction duration=30s&gt;</code> is specified,
        the contents of the transaction are executed for 30 seconds.
        By default, the transaction executes its contents only once.
        All threads or processes start executing transactions at the
        same time.
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3 id="flowop_desc"><title>Flowop</title>
        The contents of the transaction are called
        <emphasis>flowop</emphasis>s. These basic operations
        (building blocks) are used to define a workload. Current
        supported flowps are 
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>Connect</listitem>
          <listitem>Accept</listitem>
          <listitem>disconnect</listitem>
          <listitem>read</listitem>
          <listitem>write</listitem>
          <listitem>redv</listitem>
          <listitem>sendto</listitem>
          <listitem>sendfilev</listitem>
          <listitem>NOP</listitem>
          <listitem>think</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
       	<para>
	  Every Flowop has a set of options. In the XML file, these are space
	  seperated. The supported options are listed below.
	</para> 
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Common options</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <table class="options">
                  <tr><td class="fixed">count</td>
                    <td>The number of times this flowop will be
                      executed
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">duration</td>
                    <td>The amount of time this flowop will be executed.
                      Example: <code>duration=100ms</code>. 
		      <emphasis role="strong">This option will no longer be
		      supported in future versions of uperf. Specify the
		      duration in the transaction</emphasis>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">rate</td>
                    <td><emphasis role="strong">Experimental:</emphasis>
                      This option causes uperf to execute this flowop at the
                      specified rate for <code>iterations</code> or
                      <code>duration</code> seconds.
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Connect/Accept</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>writerse_option
                The connect flowop specifies that a connection needs to
                be opened. The <parameter>options</parameter> parameter
                specifies more details regaring the connection. The
                following keys are supported
                <table class="options">
                  <tr><td class="fixed">remotehost</td>
                    <td>The remote host that we need to connect or accept
                    connection from</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">protocol</td>
                    <td>The protocol used to connect to the remote host.
                    Valid values are tcp, udp, ssl, and sctp</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">tcp_nodelay</td>
                    <td>Controls whether
                      <parameter>TCP_NODELAY</parameter> is set or not
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">wndsz</td>
                    <td>Size of the socket send and receive buffer. This
                      parameter is used to set <code>SO_SNDBUF, SO_RCVBUF</code> 
                      flags using  <code>setsocktopt()</code>                    
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">engine</td>
                    <td>
                      SSL Engine.
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>                
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Read, Write, Sendto and Recv flowops</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <table class="options">
                  <tr><td class="fixed">size</td>
                    <td>Amount of data that is either read or written.
		      Uperf supports exchange of 
		     	<itemizedlist>
			  <listitem>Fixed size messages</listitem>
			  <listitem>Asymmetrical size messages</listitem>
			  <listitem>Random size messages</listitem>
			</itemizedlist> 
		      
		      For fixed size messages, the master and all slaves
		      used a fixed size for receives and transmits. For
		      asymmetrical sized messages, the slaves use the
		      size specified by the <code>rszize</code>
		      parameter. The master still uses the
		      <code>size</code> parameter.  For a random sized
		      message, the a uniformly distributed value between
		      the user specifed min and max is used by the
		      transmitting side, and the receiving side uses the
		      <emphasis>max</emphasis> as the message size.
		      Example: <code>size=64k</code> or
		      <code>size=rand(4k,8k)</code>
                    </td>
                  </tr>

		  <tr><td class="fixed">rsize</td>
                    <td>See description of asymmetrical messages above.</td>
                  </tr>

                  <tr><td class="fixed">canfail</td>
		    <td>Indicates that a failure for this flowop will
		    not cause uperf to abort. This is espcially useful
		    in UDP where a packet drop does not constitue a
		    fatal error.  This can be also be used for example,
		    to test a SYN flood attack (Threads
		    <code>connect()</code> repeatedly ignoring errors).
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">non_blocking</td>
                    <td>Use non-blocking IO. The socket/file descriptor is
                      set the NO_BLOCK flag.
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">poll_timeout</td>
                    <td>If this option is set, the thread will first
                      <code>poll</code> for specified duration before trying
                      to carry out the operation. A <code>poll</code> timeout
                      is returned as an error back to uperf.
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">conn</td>
                    <td>Every open connection is assigned a connection name.
		    Currently, the name can be any valid integer, however, uperf
		    could take a string in the future.  <code>conn</code>
		    identifies the connection to use with this flowop. This
		    connection name is thread private.
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Sendfile and Sendfilev flowops</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The sendfile flowop uses the
		   <code>sendfile(3EXT)</code> function call to transfer
		   a single file.  The sendfilev flowop transfers a set
		   of files using the <code>sendfilev(3EXT)</code>
		   interface.  Multiple files are randomly picked from
		   all transferrable files (see dir below) and
		   tranferred to the slave.
                <table class="options">
                  <tr><td class="fixed">dir</td>
                    <td>This parameter identifies the directory from
		    which the files will be transferred. The directory
		    is search recursively to generate a list of all
		    readable files.  Example: <code>dir=/space</code>
		    </td>
                   </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">nfiles</td>
                    <td>This parameter identifies the number of files
		    that will be transferred with each call to
		    <code>sendfilev(3EXT)</code>. This is used as the
		    3rd argument to the <code>sendfilev(3EXT)</code>. 
		    nfiles is assumed to be 1 for the sendfile flowop.
		    function. Example: <code>nfiles=10</code>
		    </td>
                   </tr>
                  <tr><td class="fixed">size</td>
                    <td>This parameter identifies the chunk size for the
		    transfer. Instead of sending the whole file, uperf
		    will send <emphasis>size</emphasis> sized chunks
		    one at a time. <emphasis>This is used only if 
		    nfiles=1</emphasis>
		    </td>
                   </tr>
                </table>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1><title>Statistics collected by uperf</title>
    <para>
      uperf collects quite a wide variety of statistics. By default,
      uperf prints the throughput every second while the test is
      running, and then prints out the total throughput. uperf also
      prints the network statistics, calculated independently using
      system statistics, to verify the throughput reported via uperf.
      uperf also prints statistics from all the hosts involved in this
      test to validate the output.   
    </para>
    <para>
      Some of the statistics collected by uperf are listed below
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Throughput</listitem>
        <listitem>Latency</listitem>
        <listitem>Group Statistics</listitem>
        <listitem>Per-Thread statistics</listitem>
        <listitem>Transaction Statistics</listitem>
        <listitem>Flowops Statistics</listitem>
        <listitem>Netstat Statistics</listitem>
        <listitem>Per-second Throughput</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Default uperf output</title>
      <programlisting><xi:include  href="uperf-default-output.txt"  parse="text"  
                                     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Common profiles</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>One way throughput test</title>
      <para>In a one way throughput test, we have one host transmitting
          (or receiving) data from a client. Since we are interested in
          in maximizing throughput, you need to transmit large messages
          using multiple threads or processes. The following profile
          demonstrates this. 
     </para>
     <para>
      <programlisting>
<xi:include href="throughput.xml" parse="text"
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </programlisting>
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Bi-directional test</title>
      <para>In this test, we have both the peers transmitting(or receiving)
            messages. On the master this means that there are N threads
            transmitting, and N threads receving data. The following profile
            shows how to do it.
      </para>
     <para>
      <programlisting>
<xi:include href="bidirectional.xml" parse="text"
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </programlisting>
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Connection setup/teardown test</title>
      <para>
       In this test we are interested in finding out how fast we can
       setup and teardown network connections. The following profiles
       shows how to do it
      </para>
     <para>
      <programlisting>
<xi:include href="../tests/canfail.xml" parse="text"
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </programlisting>
     </para>
 
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Throughput test with multiple hosts</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    <qandaset defaultlabel='qanda'>
      
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>What is the history behind uperf?</para></question>
	<answer><para>uperf was developed by the Performance Availablity
	Engineering group at Sun Microsystems circa 2004. It was
	originally inspired by Filebench, and developed by
            <ulink url="http://blogs.sun.com/realneel">Neelakanth Nadgir</ulink>
            and Nitin Rammanavar.
        </para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>Where can I submit bugs/feedback?</para></question>
        <answer><para>Until we have something better, please email
            <email>uperf@sun.com</email>
        </para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>How do I specify which interface to use?</para></question>
        <answer><para>uperf just specifies the host to connect to. It is
            upto the OS to determine which interface to use. You can change the
            default interface to that host by changing the routing tables
        </para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>
            Does the use of <parameter>-a</parameter> affect performance?
        </para></question>
        <answer><para>
            Since <parameter>-a</parameter> collects all kinds of statistical
            information, there is a measurable impact when the flowop is 
            lightweight (UDP TX for small packets). 
        </para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>
            Does uperf support socket autotuning on Linux?
        </para></question>
        <answer><para>Do not set the wndsz parameter.
	    uperf currently always call <code>setsocketopt()</code>, and
	    this disables autotuning on Linux, so you can't test
	    autotuning. If no window size(<code>wndsz</code>) is
	    specified in the profile, <code>setsocketopt()</code> won't
	    be called by uperf, thus enabling the autotuning on Linux
        </para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>Where can I get the uperf harness?</para></question>
        <answer><para>
	    The harness is not opensource, although if there is
	    sufficient interest, we would definetely consider
	    opensourcing it. For more details, please contact Jing
	    Zhang.
        </para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>Why do you even have a 
		<parameter>-n</parameter> option?</para></question>
        <answer><para>uperf uses a global variable to count the
	  number of bytes transferred. This is updated using atomic
	  instructions <code>atomic_add_64</code> function. However, if
	  you have thousands of threads, there is very high likelyhood
	  that many threads update this value simultaneously. causing
	  higher CPU utilization. The <parameter>-n</parameter> helps in
	  this case.
	</para></answer>

      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>Why do we have an option to do sendfilev with
	chunks?</para></question>
        <answer><para>Pallab identified an issue where chunked
	sendfilev's were faster than transferring the whole
	file in one go. This will help debug the issue.
	</para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>What does operations in the Run Statistics 
		section mean?</para>
        </question>
        <answer><para>
		Operations =  1 + flowops_executed + transactions_executed
		</para></answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <!--      
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>Sample Question</para></question>
        <answer><para>SAMPLE ANSWER</para></answer>
      </qandaentry>
 -->     
    </qandaset>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
	  <title>Named connections</title>
	  <para>
	    uperf supports named connections. To specify a name,
	    you should specify <parameter>conn=X</parameter> variable
	    in the <parameter>options</parameter> to a 
	    <parameter>connect</parameter> or <parameter>accept</parameter>
	    flowop. For example,
	    <code>
	    &lt;flowop type="connect" options="conn=2 remotehost=$h 
	    protocol=tcp&gt;</code>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If a name is not specified, the connection is an
	    <emphasis>anonymous</emphasis> connection. For any flowop,
	    if a connection is not specified, it uses the first 
	    anonymous connection.
	  </para>
  </sect1>
  
</article>




